<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://thomasmcleanjr.cv/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://thomasmcleanjr.cv/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-11-16T03:09:59+00:00</updated><id>https://thomasmcleanjr.cv/feed.xml</id><title type="html">My Portfolio</title><subtitle>My Professional Portfolio and Resume</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Connecting Cards to Documentation</title><link href="https://thomasmcleanjr.cv/cards-to-docs" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Connecting Cards to Documentation" /><published>2025-10-27T08:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-27T08:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://thomasmcleanjr.cv/cards-to-docs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thomasmcleanjr.cv/cards-to-docs"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
"What happens if I'm hit by a bus tomorrow?"
</blockquote>

<p><img src="https://media1.giphy.com/media/v1.Y2lkPTc5MGI3NjExMm5ud2V6Nmd2YW9kMWZ3aXJza2NsZGNhNXVtZTY1Ym9renFleWx0YyZlcD12MV9pbnRlcm5hbF9naWZfYnlfaWQmY3Q9Zw/1yT0KoIBdn8KzQVBJX/giphy.gif" alt="Truck-kun" /></p>

<p>There are few sayings that remain as true as this one. It’s often said when one person or a small number of people has all the important information about a project or part of the stack, but no physical documentation exists anywhere(A silo).</p>

<p>It’s something that was hammered into me since I was a junior. Documentation un-silos information, allowing any dev to pick up work and make progress. Documentation can be used to track progress as well, outside of a kanban system or whatever flavor your team uses.</p>

<p>Something recently happened that changed my approach, and I wanted to discuss it here.</p>

<h2 id="the-problem">The Problem</h2>
<p>I had to take some sudden PTO. I couldn’t check my phone or my laptop. Now, I was also the owner of a project that was nearing its deadline. I left it up to my team to finish a final piece of the project: adding some creds to connect to a client and flipping a toggle to enable some testing for an internal partner.</p>

<p>Before I left, I updated my documentation and shared links with my team.</p>

<p>Came back after a few days–not only was the testing not complete, it wasn’t even started. There was some confusion on how the creds were being used forthis integration. The seniors couldn’t help much because they didn’t know are well. Suddenly I found myself, once again as a silo. The card sat untouched til the day that I got back.</p>

<p>Why did this happen? I shared my documentation in the teams channel. I even shared the documentation with my leader before leaving. This bothered me because the project could have been complete earlier than planned, unblocking another project. This is also not the first time something like this happened.</p>

<p>During stand up, I asked, and the answer surprised me. <strong>“What documentation?”</strong></p>

<p>Our manager had to attend an RTO onsite that week, a launch of another project, and they were human. The links I shared were buried in the Teams chat.</p>

<p><strong>So, Problem: Documentation is not readily available to others due to lack of visibility.</strong>
<img src="https://media.giphy.com/media/v1.Y2lkPTc5MGI3NjExMDA2ZW40ZzZybnFoc2JzbzRneXZueDdnaHFxc2xjcGJjOTgybHA2NSZlcD12MV9naWZzX3NlYXJjaCZjdD1n/syoBxnXVugdtDkKOxw/giphy.gif" alt="My Problem" /></p>

<h2 id="the-solution-i-didnt-love">The “Solution” I Didn’t Love</h2>

<p>During retro, I asked our team, mostly the seniors, what the best practice was for sharing documentation.</p>

<p>“Put the documentation on the card” was the overall verdict.</p>

<p>I didn’t and still don’t agree with this method. What about:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The information that isn’t necessary for the work on the card but is necessary for the project as a whole?</li>
  <li>What about test cases?</li>
  <li>Requirements?</li>
  <li>What are our business partners doing on their end to help complete the project?</li>
</ul>

<p>There is so much information that may be needed. This all can’t live on a card.</p>

<h2 id="my-compromise">My Compromise</h2>

<p>I wanted me team to be able to find the documentation that was necessary for the card, on the card. I don’t want to add unnecessary documentation on the vard but still available when needed. I needed something that was unobtrusive while also very visible. So I came up with a compromise that will make my team happy and rememdy the curse of the silo.
<img src="https://media.giphy.com/media/v1.Y2lkPWVjZjA1ZTQ3amMxMnRyZ28yaXplZzY2cndtOGY2dzk2YTc3emFkbzNzOHV1bjhpMSZlcD12MV9naWZzX3JlbGF0ZWQmY3Q9Zw/BYdpzXoQskl9Yh6FAY/giphy.gif" alt="The Curse" /></p>

<p><strong>First</strong>, I started adding links to my documentation on the cards themselves. It was a happy compromise. If someone needed to figure something out and I wasn’t available, it’s right there.</p>

<p><strong>Second</strong>, on the documentation itself, I added links to the cards for the associated work. I was basically home-brewing Obsidian’s data connection web. So there can’t be any questions about what they should read and what can be skipped</p>

<h2 id="foreseen-and-unforeseen-benefits">Foreseen and unforeseen Benefits</h2>

<p>Surprisingly, this style of documentation linking came with some unforeseen benefits:</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Benefit</th>
      <th>Details</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Understanding the cards and the projects as a whole</td>
      <td>The work on the card and the User story/ Acceptance Criteria was much easier</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Epics/Stories — the group of cards — are more complete</td>
      <td>Fewer cards were added later to fill in the gaps</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>A lot less questions</td>
      <td>I’m asked a lot less questions. When I am, usually during refinement of the cards, it is something that was missing from the documentation.</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>This strategy opened up some doors for me. It made project planning and the refinement stage much more easier, allowing me to juggle multiple projects without dropping the ball. Sometimes the simplest- just linking things together- make all the difference.</p>

<p>Peace out! 🫶🏻</p>]]></content><author><name>Thomas M</name></author><category term="rants" /><category term="woek-experience" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA["What happens if I'm hit by a bus tomorrow?"]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Task Management and My Second Brain</title><link href="https://thomasmcleanjr.cv/task-management" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Task Management and My Second Brain" /><published>2025-08-26T08:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-26T08:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://thomasmcleanjr.cv/task-management</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thomasmcleanjr.cv/task-management"><![CDATA[<p>I was pairing with an intern the other day. They were a little confused about how some of my Elixir code behaved, so they started asking questions. After some back-and-forth, they hit me with a surprisingly good one: <strong>“What’s something you didn’t expect would be a challenge as a developer?”</strong></p>

<p>After sitting with that question for a while, I realized I had a few answers:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Communicating with different types of people.</li>
  <li>Writing clear documentation.</li>
  <li>Figuring out how often I need to query a database (and how much indexes matter).</li>
</ul>

<p>But there’s one challenge I almost never see talked about: <strong>task management.</strong> Sure, I hear about project management or time management — there are endless books and how‑tos on those. But what about the plain, everyday skill of juggling <em>tasks</em> as a developer? That one doesn’t get nearly enough airtime.</p>

<h2 id="how-many-tasks-do-i-usually-own">How Many Tasks Do I Usually Own?</h2>

<p>I work at a company that keeps teams pretty lean while still chasing quarterly objectives. Translation: it’s rare for anyone to own just one thing at a time. A typical week for me looks like:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>A KPI-related project with a hard deadline</strong></li>
  <li><strong>Another project aligned with a longer‑term objective</strong> (something that eventually impacts a KPI)</li>
  <li><strong>A technical improvement project</strong> (monitoring, logging, performance tuning)</li>
  <li><strong>A product manager’s “quick ask”</strong> (usually an investigation into a potential feature or product idea)</li>
</ul>

<p>And that’s just projects. Each one breaks down into many smaller tasks that all need tracking — and that’s before we even bring up being on‑call. So my daily task list is in constant flux. Priorities get reshuffled, people become unavailable, and something new is always getting dropped on my plate. It’s an overlooked aspect of “wearing many hats”: to juggle it all, I need a system. A way to track what matters now, what can wait, and what needs to be handed off.</p>

<p>Naturally, I went down the <img src="https://media.giphy.com/media/v1.Y2lkPTc5MGI3NjExMW1sajBzbnFtZ3YzODE0eGp5ZDd5b3BmNG96NXh6YzAxeGY3ZGg2YyZlcD12MV9naWZzX3NlYXJjaCZjdD1n/T1GWTCSrTr2tnsvq4k/giphy.gif" alt="rabbit hole" /> My favorite learning platform? <strong>YouTube University.</strong> After a few late nights and way too many productivity videos, I decided to give <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=m9S5I3pWz94">this recommendation</a> from Thomas Frank a try.</p>

<h2 id="the-second-brain-via-notion">The Second Brain (via Notion)</h2>

<p>A <strong>Second Brain</strong> is basically a knowledge management system — an external place to capture, organize, and connect information so your actual brain doesn’t have to juggle 300 unrelated things at once. I spun mine up in Notion.</p>

<p>Imagine a mix of:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A projects-and-tasks database</li>
  <li>A notes section</li>
  <li>A documentation hub for everything I touched It looked a whole lot like <img src="assets/images/notion.png" alt="this setup" />.</li>
</ul>

<p>At one point, my Notion workspace grew so massive that I had to contact support to help recover it. That’s when I realized: I had unintentionally created a wiki that could rival a startup’s internal knowledge base. And honestly? It wasn’t a bad thing. Notion saved me countless times when switching hats between projects. But it was also <em>overkill</em>. I didn’t need a personal encyclopedia for every little task. You’d think I learned my lesson there. I didn’t.</p>

<h2 id="obsidian-notion-the-sequel">Obsidian: Notion, the Sequel</h2>

<p>If Neovim is my Michael Jordan and Aerospace is my Scottie Pippen, then Obsidian is… let’s say Dennis Rodman.</p>

<p>Not a sports fan? Fine — if Neovim is Garrus Vakarian and Aerospace is Thane Krios, then Obsidian is Mordin Solus. Still nothing? Alright:</p>

<p>Neovim = Paladin, Aerospace = Monk, Obsidian = Cleric. Nothing, <img src="https://media.giphy.com/media/v1.Y2lkPWVjZjA1ZTQ3YXYwazMyN2hmZTBjenMxb2UzOHE1MGIxdTJpdTA3N2RuZmhmYWU4aiZlcD12MV9naWZzX3NlYXJjaCZjdD1n/gkFtBo3xl05UR9FA2Q/giphy.gif" alt="Still?" /></p>

<p>The point is: Obsidian completely changed how I was managing tasks. At first, I recreated my Notion workflow: task tables, sub-tasks, each task with its own linked note page. But that quickly led to a graveyard of dead links and pointless pages. Obsidian wasn’t the problem here — I was. I had rebuilt Notion inside of Obsidian. To make matters worse, I piled on plugins, automations, daily notes, reminders, and calendars until it all started to crumble under its own weight. My once-lightweight markdown app froze up like it was running on dial-up. Something had to change.</p>

<h2 id="my-current-minimalist-setup">My Current Minimalist Setup</h2>

<p>I finally stripped everything back down. Now my system is simple, lightweight, and portable across all my machines:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong><a href="https://taskwarrior.org/docs/start/">Taskwarrior</a></strong> for task management – a CLI tool that lets me keep tasks in their purest form, with a few optional fields for tracking what actually matters.</li>
  <li><strong><a href="https://obsidian.md">Obsidian</a></strong> for notes – yes, I kept it, but now it’s just for actual note-taking. No bloated project databases, no endless documentation dumps. I only write down what I <em>need</em>. And that’s it.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="closing-thoughts">Closing Thoughts</h2>

<p>What started as me trying to wrangle my ever-shifting list of daily tasks somehow spiraled into building a full-blown digital encyclopedia… twice. But along the way, I learned something that was simple but liberating: <strong>figuring out how to manage my tasks without them managing me.</strong></p>

<p>Peace out! 🫶🏻</p>]]></content><author><name>Thomas M</name></author><category term="setup" /><category term="rants" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I was pairing with an intern the other day. They were a little confused about how some of my Elixir code behaved, so they started asking questions. After some back-and-forth, they hit me with a surprisingly good one: “What’s something you didn’t expect would be a challenge as a developer?”]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How I Added Custom Datadog Metrics using an Unsupported Language.</title><link href="https://thomasmcleanjr.cv/datadog-metrics" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How I Added Custom Datadog Metrics using an Unsupported Language." /><published>2025-08-11T09:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-11T09:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://thomasmcleanjr.cv/datadog-metrics</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thomasmcleanjr.cv/datadog-metrics"><![CDATA[<p>First, let me address the elephant in the room: OpenTelemetry. Yes, I’m aware of the protocol, and my team could have used it. But due to some limiting factors, it wasn’t an option for us.</p>

<p>We tried it before and ran into issues. This was before I owned the project, so I don’t know all the specifics.
Our DevOps team advised against it due to constraints within our organization’s Datadog setup.
So, we needed an alternative—and I built one.</p>

<h2 id="context">Context</h2>
<p>My team was told that our existing monitoring tools would no longer be supported due to expiring contracts and a company-wide push to use Datadog instead of Grafana/Sentry. Honestly, I didn’t mind; I like Datadog a lot. I’ve used it in contract work and personal projects. But our team capacity was limited. We’d just lost both of our SMEs for monitoring/observability, we had a high-priority project that was already behind, and the clock was ticking on our expiring tools.</p>

<p>My manager asked, “Can you do this?”</p>

<p>Fresh off a large cross-team project I’d led, I was ready for something that would help my team and require a bit of creativity. This project had it all:</p>

<p>A looming deadline.
A clear high-level problem, but no technical requirements.
The need for metrics to appear in Datadog, but no official support for Elixir, and OpenTelemetry wasn’t an option.
I was in. Let’s do this.</p>

<h2 id="what-is-dogstatsd">What is DogStatsD?</h2>
<p>After some research, I discovered that Datadog provides a way to receive custom application metrics: DogStatsD.</p>

<details> <summary>DogStatsD Overview</summary>
DogStatsD is Datadog’s custom implementation of the StatsD protocol, designed to collect and aggregate application metrics. It works by having your application send metrics over UDP to a local Datadog Agent, which then forwards them to Datadog’s backend for visualization and alerting.<br /> 
<br />
The beauty of DogStatsD is its simplicity and performance: UDP is fast and non-blocking, so your application can fire off metrics without waiting for a response. Plus, DogStatsD supports advanced features like tags, service checks, and events, making it a powerful tool for custom monitoring—even if your language isn’t officially supported.
<hr />

</details>
<p>So, communicating with Datadog was possible—I just needed to give our application the ability to do so. My solution started to take shape:</p>

<p>Connect to the Datadog agent.
Create an adaptor to translate metrics into the format Datadog expects.
Add metric calls to our business logic.
Connecting to Datadog Using Statix
I decided to use the Statix library, which allows you to write directly to a Datadog StatsD server. The default host and port can be found in the library documentation.</p>

<p>First, start up the connection in application.ex:</p>

<div class="language-elixir highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>
<span class="c1"># application.ex</span>
<span class="k">def</span> <span class="n">start</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">_type</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">_args</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="k">do</span>
  <span class="ss">:ok</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="no">MyApplication</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="no">Metrics</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="no">DatadogAdaptor</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">connect</span><span class="p">()</span>
  <span class="o">...</span>
<span class="k">end</span>
</code></pre></div></div>
<p>And configure Statix in config.ex:</p>

<div class="language-elixir highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>
<span class="c1"># config.ex</span>
<span class="n">config</span> <span class="ss">:statix</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="ss">prefix:</span> <span class="s2">"sample"</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="ss">host:</span> <span class="s2">"YOUR_DATADOG_HOST"</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="ss">port:</span> <span class="no">YOUR_DATADOG_PORT</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>To use the library, simply call use in your adaptor module:</p>

<div class="language-elixir highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="c1"># DatadogAdaptor.ex</span>
<span class="k">defmodule</span> <span class="no">Metrics</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="no">DatadogAdaptor</span> <span class="k">do</span>
  <span class="kn">use</span> <span class="no">Statix</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="ss">runtime_config:</span> <span class="no">true</span>
<span class="k">end</span>
</code></pre></div></div>
<hr />

<h2 id="the-implementation">The Implementation</h2>
<p>This is the fun part—where I actually get to code, not just follow instructions.</p>

<p>I decided to use the Adapter Design Pattern. This was our team’s first adapter, but it set a precedent for future projects. (I may write a post just about adapters later.) In short, it’s a middleman layer that allows the application to interact with an otherwise incompatible interface. It also creates a single point for logic, making future changes modular and manageable.</p>

<p>Datadog Tags and Phoenix Plugs
If you’re not familiar with Datadog’s dashboard, I love how simple the filters and pages are. Datadog uses tags to filter dashboards, monitoring, APM, etc.—a very streamlined approach. For our application, we had agreed-upon required tags for each metric (I called these “global tags”), plus process-specific tags unique to each request.</p>

<p>Luckily, Phoenix (Elixir’s most famous framework) has something called a [Plug]. Plugs are a middleware-like layer that lets you add logic to your application’s request pipeline.</p>

<details> <summary>Plug and Pipeline</summary> Plugs are a great place to add logic that’s necessary for the service of the application but isn’t business logic—like monitoring. We keep plugs organized using the pipeline macro. <hr /> </details>

<div class="language-elixir highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>
<span class="c1"># MyApp_web.Router.ex</span>

<span class="n">pipeline</span> <span class="ss">:monitoring</span> <span class="k">do</span>
  <span class="n">plug</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="no">MyApp</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="no">Plug</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="no">SetMetricTags</span><span class="p">)</span>
  <span class="c1">#...</span>
<span class="k">end</span>

<span class="n">scope</span> <span class="s2">"/prior_auth"</span> <span class="k">do</span>
  <span class="n">post</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">"/investigation"</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="no">InsuranceInvestigationController</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="ss">:create</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="k">end</span>
</code></pre></div></div>
<p>Since my logic isn’t business logic and needs to affect every request for this endpoint, I created a plug that I can add to the pipeline:</p>

<div class="language-elixir highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>
<span class="k">defmodule</span> <span class="no">MyApp</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="no">Plug</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="no">SetMetricTags</span> <span class="k">do</span>
  <span class="kn">import</span> <span class="no">Plug</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="no">Conn</span>

  <span class="k">def</span> <span class="n">init</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">options</span><span class="p">),</span> <span class="k">do</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="n">options</span>

  <span class="k">def</span> <span class="n">call</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">conn</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">_options</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="k">do</span>
    <span class="n">router</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">conn</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">private</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">phoenix_router</span>
    <span class="n">request_path</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">conn</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">request_path</span>
    <span class="n">method</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">conn</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">method</span>

    <span class="p">%{</span><span class="ss">plug:</span> <span class="n">controller</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="ss">plug_opts:</span> <span class="n">controller_function</span><span class="p">}</span> <span class="o">=</span>
      <span class="no">Phoenix</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="no">Router</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">route_info</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">router</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">method</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">request_path</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s2">""</span><span class="p">)</span>

    <span class="n">metric_tags</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">[</span>
      <span class="s2">"controller:</span><span class="si">#{</span><span class="n">to_string</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">controller</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="s2">"</span><span class="p">,</span>
      <span class="s2">"is_test_message:</span><span class="si">#{</span><span class="n">conn</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">assigns</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="ss">:is_test_message</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">||</span> <span class="no">false</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="s2">"</span><span class="p">,</span>
      <span class="s2">"route:</span><span class="si">#{</span><span class="n">request_path</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="s2">"</span>
    <span class="p">]</span>

    <span class="no">Process</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">put</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="ss">:metric_tags</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">metric_tags</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="n">assign</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">conn</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="ss">:metric_tags</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">metric_tags</span><span class="p">)</span>
  <span class="k">end</span>
<span class="k">end</span>
</code></pre></div></div>
<hr />

<p>This adds the list of metric_tags to the process dictionary, making them globally available throughout the application. We’ll add request-specific tags when we create the metric itself.</p>

<h3 id="metric-adapter-and-request-specific-tags">Metric Adapter and Request-Specific Tags</h3>
<p>Finally, the adapter. The objectives here:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Create the metric name.</li>
  <li>Retrieve the global tags from the SetMetricTags plug.</li>
  <li>Add process-specific tags and combine them with the global tags.</li>
</ul>

<p>Since this was a first for me, my main focus was readability and clarity. Most of the devs on my team hadn’t done something like this before, so it was on me to make it clear for everyone—senior, mid, and junior alike.</p>

<p>First, let’s pull the global metrics. Datadog requires them to be a list/array of strings.</p>

<details> <summary>Breakdown of the Elixir Code Below</summary> If you’re not familiar, this may look confusing. 
  Elixir allows two things:<br /> 
  |-&gt; <b>Function Header Pattern Matching:</b> You can destructure a function’s parameters directly in the header, as long as they match the expected type. <br /> 
  |-&gt; <b>Overloading:</b> You can define multiple functions with the same name but different parameters, creating different implementations. 
<hr />
</details>

<div class="language-elixir highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>
<span class="c1"># MyApp.Metrics.MetricsAdaptor</span>

<span class="k">defp</span> <span class="n">collect_module_tags</span><span class="p">([</span><span class="n">_</span> <span class="o">|</span> <span class="n">_</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">module_tags</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="k">do</span>
  <span class="no">Enum</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">map</span><span class="p">(</span>
    <span class="n">module_tags</span><span class="p">,</span>
    <span class="k">fn</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="n">key</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">value</span><span class="p">}</span> <span class="o">-&gt;</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="si">#{</span><span class="n">key</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="s2">:</span><span class="si">#{</span><span class="n">value</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="s2">"</span> <span class="k">end</span>
  <span class="p">)</span>
<span class="k">end</span>

<span class="k">defp</span> <span class="n">collect_module_tags</span><span class="p">([]),</span> <span class="k">do</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="p">[]</span>

<span class="k">defp</span> <span class="n">collect_module_tags</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">module_tags</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="k">do</span>
  <span class="k">raise</span> <span class="s2">"Tags passed into Metrics.increment directly from the module should be a list. Attempted tags: </span><span class="si">#{</span><span class="n">module_tags</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="s2">"</span>
<span class="k">end</span>
</code></pre></div></div>
<p>This logic combines the request-specific tags and the global tags into a single list. Next, I sanitize the metric names for uniformity:</p>

<div class="language-elixir highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>
<span class="c1"># MyApp.Metrics.MetricsAdaptor</span>

<span class="nv">@spec</span> <span class="n">sanitize_metric_name</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">term</span><span class="p">())</span> <span class="p">::</span> <span class="no">String</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">t</span><span class="p">()</span>
<span class="k">def</span> <span class="n">sanitize_metric_name</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">metric</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="ow">when</span> <span class="n">is_binary</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">metric</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="k">do</span>
  <span class="no">String</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">replace</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">metric</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s2">" "</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s2">"_"</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="k">end</span>

<span class="k">def</span> <span class="n">sanitize_metric_name</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">metric</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="k">do</span>
  <span class="n">metric</span>
  <span class="o">|&gt;</span> <span class="n">inspect</span> <span class="c1"># Returns a binary metric name</span>
  <span class="o">|&gt;</span> <span class="n">sanitize_metric_name</span>
<span class="k">end</span>
</code></pre></div></div>
<hr />
<h4 id="result">Result:</h4>

<p>Metric Name Sanitization: Convert external request → Convert_external_request
Tag List: [is_test_message: true, controller: “/benefit_investigation”] → [“is_test_message:true”, “controller:/benefit_investigation”]
With the tags combined and metric names sanitized, we’re ready to send metrics to the Datadog agent.</p>

<div class="language-elixir highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>
<span class="c1"># Datadog.Tags.ex</span>

<span class="k">def</span> <span class="n">fetch</span> <span class="k">do</span>
  <span class="k">case</span> <span class="no">Process</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">get</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="ss">:metric_tags</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="k">do</span>
    <span class="no">nil</span> <span class="o">-&gt;</span> <span class="sd">"""
    Failed to retrieve the :metric_tags from Process Dictionary.
    """</span>
    <span class="n">metric_tags</span> <span class="o">-&gt;</span> <span class="c1"># Catch-all</span>
      <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">is_list</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">metric_tags</span><span class="p">),</span> <span class="k">do</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="n">metric_tags</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="k">else</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="no">List</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">wrap</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">metric_tags</span><span class="p">)</span>
  <span class="k">end</span>
<span class="k">end</span>

<span class="c1"># MyApp.Metrics.MetricsAdaptor</span>

<span class="kn">use</span> <span class="no">Statix</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="ss">runtime_config:</span> <span class="no">true</span>

<span class="nv">@doc</span> <span class="s2">"Increment/2 increases/adds a metric to Datadog by 1"</span>
<span class="nv">@spec</span> <span class="n">increment</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="no">String</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">t</span><span class="p">(),</span> <span class="n">list</span><span class="p">())</span> <span class="p">::</span> <span class="ss">:ok</span>
<span class="k">def</span> <span class="n">increment</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">metric</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">tags</span> <span class="p">\\</span> <span class="p">[])</span> <span class="k">do</span>
  <span class="n">datadog_tags</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="no">Tags</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">fetch</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="o">++</span> <span class="n">collect_module_tags</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">tags</span><span class="p">)</span>
  <span class="no">Statix</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">increment</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">metric</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="ss">tags:</span> <span class="n">datadog_tags</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="k">end</span>
</code></pre></div></div>
<hr />
<p>Now, I just need to call the increment/2 function in my business logic and—boom!—the metric appears in Datadog. I can’t show our business logic, but when I’m done with my side project (which uses a similar implementation), I’ll add screenshots below.</p>

<p>Example of the finished product in Datadog:</p>

<p><img src="../assets/images/datadog-metrics.png" alt="Datadog Metrics" /></p>

<h2 id="what-would-i-change-and-an-idea">What Would I Change? (And an Idea)</h2>
<p>I’m not a fan of calling Metric.increment directly within business logic. I know, we’re starting to wade into Elixir/Functional’s “no side effects” territory! Allow me a quick soapbox moment: side effects are only a problem when they’re hidden and untraceable. By keeping them minimal and well-documented, it’s manageable.</p>

<p>That said, I had an idea: a decorator-like implementation that watches for certain logic and then triggers the Metric.increment call. There’s a lot to figure out, but maybe a library or something similar could combine aspect-oriented programming, OpenTelemetry, and some kind of event watcher. I think it could be really useful.</p>]]></content><author><name>Thomas M</name></author><category term="work-experience" /><category term="tech-stack" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[First, let me address the elephant in the room: OpenTelemetry. Yes, I’m aware of the protocol, and my team could have used it. But due to some limiting factors, it wasn’t an option for us.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Persistence Over Perfection, My Journey to Software Engineering</title><link href="https://thomasmcleanjr.cv/my-journey" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Persistence Over Perfection, My Journey to Software Engineering" /><published>2025-08-11T08:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-11T08:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://thomasmcleanjr.cv/my-journey</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thomasmcleanjr.cv/my-journey"><![CDATA[<p>If there’s one thing I’ve learned about myself, it’s that I rarely do things the “normal” way. While everyone else was busy racking up points in the Accelerated Reading program with the usual suspects—Magic Tree House, Diary of a Wimpy Kid, Harry Potter—I was more interested in hacking my way through Deus Ex Machina: Human Evolution or setting my alarm for 4 a.m. to catch Cowboy Bebop reruns. I’ve always had a knack for finding my own path, especially when the standard route just didn’t make sense to me.</p>

<p>Let’s rewind a bit. In elementary school, my reading scores were so low that my teachers wanted to hold me back a year. The school had this AR program where you had to rack up points by reading certain books. Magic Tree House? Diary of a Wimpy Kid? Harry Potter? Sorry, not for me. I wanted something with a little more edge. My teacher, probably at her wit’s end, finally just let me loose in the library. “Pick anything,” she said. I came back with a Tom Clancy novel—four reading levels above where I was “supposed” to be. Political intrigue, shadow governments, the threat of World War III. Now that was a story. By the time they scrapped the AR program, I had one of the highest point totals in the school.</p>

<p>Fast forward to high school, and I was the kid who set his alarm for 4 a.m. just to watch anime that wasn’t even meant for my age group. I’d do my homework while the rest of the house slept, then make sure everyone else was up for school and work. I guess you could say I’ve always been a little… unconventional.</p>

<p>When I started college in 2012, I was working 40 hours a week and going to school full-time. At first, I tried to do it all—show up to every class, ace every test, be the model student. Spoiler: I was burning out fast. So I did what I do best—I changed my approach. I mapped out the labs, test days, and project deadlines, and focused my energy there. Suddenly, my grades improved and I actually had time to sleep. Who knew?</p>

<p>So when it came time to break into tech, I knew the “traditional” path wasn’t for me. I wasn’t about to take on more debt for a CS degree, and bootcamps felt like a stress marathon. I figured, if I could teach myself how to survive college and work, I could teach myself to code. I just needed a plan, some mentors, and a place where I could learn from my mistakes.</p>

<p>Here’s how I mapped it out (with a little help from Disney’s funniest meme-worthy character):
<img src="https://media.giphy.com/media/v1.Y2lkPTc5MGI3NjExYzdwaTl6Ymt5NXV5OG9jaThreW96cDhvOTF5bXI1cjJ2dGtpYnV5aiZlcD12MV9naWZzX3NlYXJjaCZjdD1n/KEYEpIngcmXlHetDqz/giphy.gif" alt="It's all coming together" /></p>

<ul>
  <li>Get a job—any job—in a tech company.</li>
  <li>Find a mentor who actually knows what they’re doing.</li>
  <li>Learn to code, then learn to program, then learn to build real applications.</li>
  <li>Build a resume with actual projects, not just certificates.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="rolling-the-dice-getting-my-foot-in-the-door">Rolling the Dice: Getting My Foot in the Door</h3>
<p><img src="https://media.giphy.com/media/v1.Y2lkPTc5MGI3NjExZDIzaG1zZmlyc3U0Z3E2dWRzY3B3Zm5rcDRwZWRxbDhkNGJucTEzMSZlcD12MV9naWZzX3NlYXJjaCZjdD1n/8iMATxhUkFkeEwnjfq/giphy.gif" alt="Nat 20" />
My first “tech” job? Office worker at a healthcare/pharma tech company in my hometown. The company helped doctors and patients with prescription authorizations, and let’s just say, a lot of those authorizations failed because of missing data. (I’ll skip the interview story, but let’s just say I rolled a Nat 20 on my persuasion check.)</p>

<p>The real challenge was moving from the call center to anything even remotely related to software. Meanwhile, I was teaching myself Java (my first language), then Python, and figuring out Django. I was basically building my own curriculum, one Google search at a time.</p>

<p>Then, I got picked for a test group at work. We were supposed to try a new workflow for prior authorizations—call the pharmacy first, not the insurance company. By the end of the quarter, I was leading the project, reporting to leadership, learning SQL, and even suggesting ways to improve our workflow. Not bad for a guy who started out answering phones.</p>

<h3 id="mentorship-the-game-changer">Mentorship: The Game Changer</h3>
<p>Enter Dan, my mentor. If it wasn’t for him, I probably would’ve stalled out after the test group project. The company had this stretch program for aspiring software engineers. Most people went back to their day jobs, but a few of us got a shot at an apprenticeship. Dan’s advice?
Stop doing tutorials. Stop just reading textbooks.</p>

<p>Write code, write code badly.
Figure out why it’s bad.
Write it again, but better.
So I did. I built a web scraper, a D&amp;D manager, and a bunch of other projects in Python. When it came time to apply for the program, I knew the competition would be tough. Three interviews, three teams, three different sets of expectations. The program was new, so every interview was a little different, but they all wanted to see if you could actually build something.</p>

<h3 id="facing-my-weaknesses-the-front-end-challenge">Facing My Weaknesses: The Front-End Challenge</h3>
<p>The first interview? Full-stack team, but with a front-end focus—specifically Vue.js. At that point, my front-end experience was basically “I know what a button looks like.” I’d spent most of my time on backend projects, so JavaScript frameworks and dynamic UIs were a whole new world.</p>

<p>They gave me some sample code to review and asked me questions about it. I could walk through the code and explain what it was doing, but when they asked about my own experience or real-world front-end projects, I didn’t have much to say. I realized pretty quickly that while I could reason through code, I didn’t have the hands-on experience that comes from actually building and debugging front-end apps.</p>

<p>It was humbling, for sure. My backend skills weren’t enough to carry me through a full-stack interview—especially when the team wanted someone comfortable with Vue.js and modern JavaScript. I didn’t get negative feedback, but it was clear my lack of front-end experience was a gap.</p>

<p>But here’s the thing: I didn’t let it get me down. After the interview, I added JavaScript and Vue.js to my “to-learn” list. I started exploring tutorials, building small projects, and messing around with component-based development. Even though I eventually decided to focus more on backend, that experience taught me the importance of being adaptable and willing to step outside my comfort zone.</p>

<p>Looking back, I’m actually grateful for that interview. It showed me a weakness, but it also gave me a clear direction for growth. In tech, there’s always something new to learn—and that’s half the fun.</p>

<h3 id="finding-my-groove-with-ruby">Finding My Groove with Ruby</h3>
<p><img src="https://media.giphy.com/media/v1.Y2lkPWVjZjA1ZTQ3dGh4Nm01YWJvNnpvMjJkc295b2VxdjdsMTkzanEwM2V4eGUzNmkwZiZlcD12MV9naWZzX3NlYXJjaCZjdD1n/2jOcXFwhIEypPeQvOY/giphy.gif" alt="Thinking" />
The second interview was for a full-stack team using Ruby on Rails. Since I had Python experience, Ruby wasn’t a big stretch. I explained my D&amp;D project and how I built it. I thought I was out of the running, but then another manager, Matt, reached out for an interview.</p>

<p>Matt focused on my motivations and how I planned to teach myself.
“This program is simply a mentorship. You will be teaching yourself most of the time.”</p>

<p>I started with his team, working two days a week with two mentors. I began with Codecademy’s Ruby courses, then moved on to small challenges. I needed to complete a final project to be evaluated.</p>

<p>At first, I struggled. During pair sessions, I didn’t understand the “magic” of Ruby, which made debugging harder. My mentor was direct:
“We are expecting you to perform better than this.”
Some of the feedback:</p>

<p>Better test cases: Test the logic, think of real-world situations, invalid inputs, and unexpected code.
Better debugging: Use debugging tools, not just print statements. Find the root cause, not just the symptoms.
That weekend, I took a hard look at myself. I didn’t want to go back to the call center. If I was behind, I needed a plan to catch up.</p>

<p>That Tuesday, I called a meeting with my manager and mentors:
“I’d like to change our approach. I got some feedback, and I think this is how I can not only fix my issues but actually become a better developer if we…”</p>

<h4 id="my-new-approach">My new approach:</h4>

<p>A small project every week
Write test cases for every challenge/kata
Drive during pair sessions, with mentors only helping when I’m stuck
I improved, but the news of my shift to backend made me think that I was still behind.</p>

<h3 id="the-mastermind-challenge-my-capstone-project">The Mastermind Challenge: My Capstone Project</h3>
<p>For the final project, we chose the Mastermind game from The Odin Project. Requirements included:</p>

<p>Bot option
Player vs. player mode
Login screen
Display previous guesses
During the presentation, a bug appeared: the login screen would reappear when the user chose player vs. player, causing a loop. I didn’t realize at the time, but in the chat, I was told to just display the bot walkthrough.</p>

<p>I assumed everyone was troubleshooting during their presentations, so I went for it. I started by replicating another controller/integration test I’d created for player vs. player. The login information was supposed to set the session’s ID, but I realized there was some carryover from a previous test. I removed it and suddenly, the test failed. I checked the controller file—it was misconfigured. The session wasn’t being set before calling the player vs. player option, which routed back to the login page. A quick Stack Overflow search helped me set the session correctly. The login loop disappeared, and the app worked.</p>

<p>After the presentation, I was sent back to the call center for the rest of the week, and the program ended. I reached out to Matt for feedback and advice on my resume. For me, this experience cemented my decision: this is what I want to do, at this company or another.</p>

<p>Matt told me, “I probably shouldn’t tell you this yet, but that presentation was the interview. We’re hiring you as a junior on our team.”</p>

<p>Twelve devs in the program, three spots. In the end, I earned one of those spots and officially became a software engineer that year—four years ago.
<img src="https://media.giphy.com/media/v1.Y2lkPTc5MGI3NjExMWszaDEzbzNzdWZlY2p6djVlbHByYTdpZ2J3bGY4NnBwbnJ3MWFyaiZlcD12MV9naWZzX3NlYXJjaCZjdD1n/xLR6VXtm3kBZytYw73/giphy.gif" alt="I Don't know how but" /></p>

<h3 id="growth-grit-and-what-comes-next">Growth, Grit, and What Comes Next</h3>
<p>The hardest part of my journey? Learning to communicate problems and solutions using developer vocabulary. The moment I realized I was in trouble—not meeting my mentor’s expectations—was also the moment I’m most proud of. I used introspection and persistence to improve.</p>

<p>My advice:
Learn to code, learn to write programs, then build side projects. Stick to one language until you’re comfortable.</p>

<p>My current goals:
I’m looking for a job I can be passionate about, where I can help others. I’m also working on a TTRPG site that allows players and GMs to play any tabletop game online.</p>

<p>If you’re on an unconventional path, keep going. Persistence and adaptability are your best tools. And if you ever feel lost, confused, or unsure of an answer—whether you’re behind a keyboard or just trying to figure out your next move—remember:</p>

<p>The process is just as important as the solution.</p>]]></content><author><name>Thomas M</name></author><category term="whoami" /><category term="work-experience" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[If there’s one thing I’ve learned about myself, it’s that I rarely do things the “normal” way. While everyone else was busy racking up points in the Accelerated Reading program with the usual suspects—Magic Tree House, Diary of a Wimpy Kid, Harry Potter—I was more interested in hacking my way through Deus Ex Machina: Human Evolution or setting my alarm for 4 a.m. to catch Cowboy Bebop reruns. I’ve always had a knack for finding my own path, especially when the standard route just didn’t make sense to me.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How Bartending Made Me a Better Problem Solver</title><link href="https://thomasmcleanjr.cv/how-bartending-made-me-a-better-problem-solver" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Bartending Made Me a Better Problem Solver" /><published>2025-08-07T08:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-07T08:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://thomasmcleanjr.cv/how-bartending-made-me-a-better-problem-solver</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thomasmcleanjr.cv/how-bartending-made-me-a-better-problem-solver"><![CDATA[<p>I don’t remember exactly when I caught the coding bug. Maybe it started when I played Skyrim with a mod that was no longer being updated, and decided to fix it myself. Or maybe it was when I picked up <em>Automate the Boring Stuff with Python</em> and learned Python just for fun. I even learned some HTML and CSS back in high school, making a scrolling banner on a static page.</p>

<p>But what I do know is that I’ve always loved problem-solving and creating something for others to enjoy. The funny thing is, I didn’t really become good at it until I became a bartender.</p>

<p>I’m forever grateful for my time as a server and bartender. The lessons I learned from meeting and talking to new people every day were invaluable. The biggest challenge? When someone would ask, “Can you make me a salty yet sweet drink, but not a margarita?” Suddenly, I had to come up with a solution on the spot for a complete stranger. That’s a tough problem—even on the slowest days.</p>

<hr />

<p>At first, my approach was to learn everything about every spirit at the bar. Bourbon vs. scotch. Why some cocktails are shaken and others stirred. When to use Beefeater vs. Tanqueray. Sometimes this worked, but other times it was a complete failure—even when I thought I understood the guest’s taste. What was I missing?</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Give me six hours to chop down a tree and I will spend the first four sharpening the axe.”<br />
— Abraham Lincoln</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I realized my process was the problem. I didn’t have ten years of experience, and I was trying to be perfect on the first try. Sure, I could follow a recipe and replicate a classic drink, but that rarely impressed anyone. So, I started doing what I now do in coding: I start with the process. What steps do I need to get to a solution?</p>

<p>Let’s go back to that “not a margarita” request. Here were the requirements:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Refreshing (it was a hot day, and it was brunch!)</li>
  <li>Tequila, but not too forward (the taste shouldn’t be overpowering)</li>
  <li>Still salty</li>
</ul>

<p>So, basically a margarita—but not a margarita. I had my objectives. Next, I started building. Tequila would play a main role, but I needed to keep it balanced. Lime is an easy way to add refreshment, and if you get the balance right, it can carry the drink.</p>

<p>Here’s where the process comes in. I’d make enough of the drink to taste it, grab a straw, and test. This wasn’t a fancy New York bar, but once I started tasting and testing my experiments, I could narrow down the solution. The guest watching me loved watching my process.</p>

<p>Of course, I needed a sweetener, but simple syrup would be too much. We had honey syrup, which is lighter and pairs well with tequila and lime. Another taste—getting closer, but still missing the salty component. I also wanted this drink to be a real departure from a standard margarita.</p>

<p>It was a hot Saturday brunch downtown, and I spotted a bottle of champagne. Sometimes, creative solutions are necessary. After shaking the spirits, I poured the cocktail into a glass, floated some champagne on top, added a pinch of salt, and finished with a lime flag. One final end-to-end taste, and I handed it to the guest for review.</p>

<p>She loved it. In fact, I made that drink for her every time she came in. I kept the recipe for myself, but I did share it with her before I left that job.</p>

<hr />
<p>If you ever feel lost, confused, or unsure of an answer—whether you’re behind the bar or behind a keyboard—I recommend looking at your process and seeing where things start to break down:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Do you really understand the problem?</li>
  <li>Can you break it down into smaller parts?</li>
  <li>Are you creating and testing solutions along the way?</li>
</ul>

<p>Knowing the problem gets you close, but understanding and refining your process can make your solution bulletproof.</p>

<p>Have a good one.</p>]]></content><author><name>Thomas M</name></author><category term="whoami" /><category term="work-experience" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I don’t remember exactly when I caught the coding bug. Maybe it started when I played Skyrim with a mod that was no longer being updated, and decided to fix it myself. Or maybe it was when I picked up Automate the Boring Stuff with Python and learned Python just for fun. I even learned some HTML and CSS back in high school, making a scrolling banner on a static page.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My Dev Setup</title><link href="https://thomasmcleanjr.cv/my-setup" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Dev Setup" /><published>2025-08-07T08:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-07T08:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://thomasmcleanjr.cv/my-setup</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thomasmcleanjr.cv/my-setup"><![CDATA[<h1 id="my-setup-and-how-i-use-it">My Setup and How I Use It</h1>

<p>I’m not going to walk you through my entire setup, but I do want to highlight the stars of the show. This isn’t a step-by-step guide—think of it as a list of recommendations. As a self-taught dev, I picked up most of these tools while troubleshooting completely unrelated problems. Maybe they’ll help you too.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="-chapter-1-note-taking--offloading-my-brain">📝 Chapter 1: Note-taking &amp; Offloading My Brain</h2>

<p><strong>TL;DR:</strong> I can’t recommend Obsidian enough. I don’t use it to replace my brain, just to offload some of the mental clutter.</p>

<p>If you’ve ever dabbled in organization, project management, or even been a Game Master (iykyk), you might have heard of <a href="https://obsidian.md/">Obsidian</a>. At its core, it’s a note-taking app—but what makes it special is its approach. Obsidian is a JavaScript-based app that stores your notes as Markdown files on your computer.</p>

<h3 id="sub-title"> Plugins I use</h3>

<details>
<summary>I Use These in Every Vault: (Click to expand)</summary>
    <br />

<summary>Dataview:</summary> |-&gt;
    Think of Dataview as a way to turn your notes into a mini-database. It lets you write queries (using a simple language) to pull information from your notes and display it in tables, lists, or even as tasks. For example, you can create a table of all notes tagged with `#project` or list all tasks due this week. It’s perfect for tracking projects, tasks, or any kind of structured data. <br />

<summary>Tasks:</summary> |-&gt; 
    The Tasks plugin supercharges your to-do lists in Obsidian. It lets you create, manage, and query tasks across all your notes. You can filter tasks by status, due date, or tags, and even see them in a summary view. If you like keeping your tasks close to your notes (instead of a separate app), this is a must-have. <br />

<summary>Kanban:</summary>  |-&gt; 
    Kanban brings Trello-style boards right into Obsidian. You can organize your projects visually, moving cards between columns like “To Do,” “In Progress,” and “Done.” It’s great for managing workflows, tracking progress, or just getting a bird’s-eye view of what you’re working on—all without leaving your notes. <br />

</details>

<hr />

<h2 id="️-chapter-2-alias-everything">🛤️ Chapter 2: Alias Everything</h2>

<p>If you work in the terminal and find yourself typing the same commands over and over, you need to start using aliases.</p>

<p>An <strong>alias</strong> is a shortcut for a longer or more complex command. It saves time and keystrokes. Even for simple commands, I use aliases to make my workflow smoother.</p>

<p><strong>Besides <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">git</code>, the most commonly aliased command is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">ls</code>.</strong> Here are my favorites:</p>

<p>Bash</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>alias ll='ls -lh'   # Long format, human-readable sizes
alias la='ls -la'   # List all files, including hidden ones
alias l='ls -CF'    # List files in columns
</code></pre></div></div>

<hr />

<h2 id="-chapter-3-modern-command-line-toolkit">🔨 Chapter 3: Modern Command Line Toolkit</h2>

<p>When I was a junior dev, I focused on mastering programming and did things the hard way for a while. Eventually, I discovered newer CLI tools that made my life so much easier. You can stick with the classics, but modern alternatives often improve on the old tools like <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">ls</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cd</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">grep</code>, and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">find</code>.</p>

<h3 id="ezaa-betterls"><strong>Eza:</strong> A Better <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">ls</code></h3>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Why I like it:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Pretty colors and syntax highlighting</li>
      <li>Stack and grid layouts (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">eza --grid</code>)</li>
      <li>File icons (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">eza -l --grid --icons</code>)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Docs:</strong> <a href="https://eza.rocks/">eza.rocks</a></li>
</ul>

<h3 id="fzffuzzy-finder-for-everything"><strong>FZF:</strong> Fuzzy Finder for Everything</h3>

<p>Ever forget the name of a file or config? <a href="https://github.com/junegunn/fzf"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">fzf</code></a> is a fuzzy finder that searches files, folders, and even command history. I stopped using Spotlight after I found this (until I discovered Raycast, but that’s another story).</p>

<h3 id="zoxidesmartercd"><strong>Zoxide:</strong> Smarter <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cd</code></h3>

<p><a href="https://github.com/ajeetdsouza/zoxide"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">zoxide</code></a> remembers your most-used directories and lets you jump to them instantly. No more typing out long paths—just type <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">z &lt;folder&gt;</code> and you’re there.</p>

<h3 id="tldrsimple-cli-help"><strong>tldr:</strong> Simple CLI Help</h3>

<p>Ever see a command you don’t recognize? <a href="https://tldr.sh/"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">tldr</code></a> gives you simple, community-driven explanations and examples for CLI tools. It’s like having a helpful dev friend on call.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="-aerospace-simple-window-tiling-manager">🚀 Aerospace: Simple Window Tiling Manager</h2>

<p>If you’re reading this, you’re probably a power user (or on your way). Once you try a window tiling manager, you might become a fanatic like me. A tiling manager organizes your open windows into non-overlapping tiles, maximizing screen space and improving workflow.</p>

<p><strong>Why use one?</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>Assign windows to workspaces and switch with hotkeys</li>
  <li>Arrange windows in your preferred layout</li>
  <li>Create a keyboard-driven dev experience</li>
  <li>Make the most of large screens</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Heads up:</strong> If you prefer minimal open windows, this might not be for you. But for my ADHD brain, it’s a lifesaver—I can keep everything open and visible, so nothing gets forgotten.</p>

<hr />

<p><strong>Peace out!</strong> 🫶🏻</p>]]></content><author><name>Thomas M</name></author><category term="work-experience" /><category term="tech-stack" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My Setup and How I Use It]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hello! My Name is Thomas McLean</title><link href="https://thomasmcleanjr.cv/welcome" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hello! My Name is Thomas McLean" /><published>2025-08-04T10:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-04T10:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://thomasmcleanjr.cv/welcome</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thomasmcleanjr.cv/welcome"><![CDATA[<p>
I'm a self-taught full-stack developer that enjoys tackling new challenges and is known for their ability to improve quickly using introspection and problem-solving. Ask me about one of my ongoing projects. Check out some of my projects.
</p>

<hr />

<header>
  <h1 id="Work">📁 Work</h1>
</header>

<h3 id="role">📁 Current Role</h3>

<p>
I serve as a Product/Integration Engineer, where I am involved in the entire lifecycle of product implementation, from initial brainstorming to project completion. My responsibilities encompass design, implementation, testing, and deployment, which has allowed me to gain experience with a diverse range of technologies.
</p>

<h3 id="responsibilities">📁 Key Responsibilities</h3>

<h6>My primary focus is on developing solutions that enable both internal and external stakeholders to effectively investigate insurance coverage. This includes:</h6>

<ul>
  <li>
    <strong>Discovering Updated Insurance Coverage:</strong>
    Ensuring that users have access to the latest information regarding insurance policies.
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>Managing Prior Authorization Updates:</strong>
    Keeping track of changes in prior authorization requirements.
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>Identifying Drug Alternatives:</strong>
    Providing options for alternative medications when necessary.
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
Additionally, I am frequently assigned Proof of Concept (POC) projects to test market viability. If a product or feature demonstrates success, I collaborate with the team to prepare it for production and subsequently hand it off to another team for further development.
</p>

<header>
  <h2 id="insights">📁 Daily Insights</h2>
</header>
<h6>In my daily activities, I engage in the following tasks:</h6>

<ul>
  <div class="insight-card">
    <li><strong>Technical Leader:</strong>
    Source of Technical knowledge for projects and applications. I field questions for our teams products and projects. Provide context of why future projects are important. Design project plans and timelines of work for future products. Give level design plans for Products in the Proof of concept phase.</li>
  </div>
  <div class="insight-card">
    <li><strong>Implementation:</strong>
    Translate design and concepts into functioning software systems. This includes coding, testing, integrating internal and external components to meet acceptance criteria of our products or set by our product managers.</li>
  </div>
  <div class="insight-card">
    <li><strong>Mentorship and Review:</strong>
    Assist in the growth of Junior and fellow mid level Engineers in development concepts and design patterns. Review pull request, complete risk assessments and provide retrospection for issues effecting external applications.</li>
  </div>
  <div class="insight-card">
    <li><strong>Cross Team/Cross Companies Communication and Assistance:</strong>
    Facilitate communication between teams and companies to ensure alignment on technical requirements and project goals. Assist in resolving technical issues that span multiple teams or companies, ensuring smooth collaboration and timely delivery of projects.</li>
  </div>
</ul>

<header>
  <h2 id="insights">📁 Quarterly Insights</h2>
</header>
<h6>In my quarterly activities, I engage in the following tasks:</h6>

<ul>
  <div class="insight-card">
    <li><strong>API Development:</strong>
    Create and maintain internal APIs that facilitate data exchange between internal customers and external clients.</li>
  </div>
  <div class="insight-card">
    <li><strong>Front-End Development:</strong>
    Build and enhance front-end applications for both internal and external users.</li>
  </div>
  <div class="insight-card">
    <li><strong>Technical Planning:</strong>
    Develop project-specific technical requirements and establish technical standards for integrations and other projects.</li>
  </div>
  <div class="insight-card">
    <li><strong>Scalable Architecture Design:</strong>
    Designed a scalable microservices architecture that improved system performance and reduced downtime. Led a project to optimize database queries and indexing strategies.</li>
  </div>
  <div class="insight-card">
    <li><strong>Product Ideation:</strong>
    Deconstruct new product ideas to effectively plan and organize technical work across multiple applications.</li>
  </div>
</ul>

<header>
  <h2 id="insights">📁 Achievements</h2>
</header>
<h6>My Recent Achievements</h6>

<ul>
  <div class="insight-card">
    <li><strong>Gateway API Solution:</strong>
    My team was previously paying ~$300,000 annually for a Gateway API that enabled our application to connect to two vendors. After a cost-to-time analysis, I designed and implemented a solution that allowed our team to cancel the contract and eliminate this expense.</li>
  </div>
  <div class="insight-card">
    <li><strong>Application Monitoring:</strong>
    Leadership has directed that our team will no longer use Grafana and Sentry for monitoring applications in the future. To ensure application health, product performance, and efficient troubleshooting, I implemented logic to integrate our applications with Datadog, an observability platform.</li>
  </div>
  <div class="insight-card">
    <li><strong>Prior Authorization Status Check:</strong>
    Previously, our team spent thousands of man hours manually contacting insurance companies to update statuses on prior authorizations. I developed an API to automate the retrieval of PA statuses, significantly reducing costs. This solution supports a product that generates over ~$20 million in revenue annually and saves the company millions in expenditures.</li>
  </div>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Thomas M</name></author><category term="whoami" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I'm a self-taught full-stack developer that enjoys tackling new challenges and is known for their ability to improve quickly using introspection and problem-solving. Ask me about one of my ongoing projects. Check out some of my projects.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Experienced Technologies</title><link href="https://thomasmcleanjr.cv/my-technologies" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Experienced Technologies" /><published>2025-08-04T08:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-04T08:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://thomasmcleanjr.cv/my-technologies</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thomasmcleanjr.cv/my-technologies"><![CDATA[<!DOCTYPE html>
<html lang="en">
<head>
    <meta charset="UTF-8">
    <title>List of Technologies that I have experience in.</title>
    <style>
        .icon {
            width: 48px;
            height: 48px;
            vertical-align: middle;
            margin-right: 8px;
            transition: transform 0.3s ease-in-out;
            display: inline-block;
        }
        .icon:hover {
            transform: scale(2.0);
        }
        ul {
            margin: 0;
            padding-left: 18px;
        }
        ul li {
            margin-bottom: 2px;
        }
        td {
            vertical-align: top;
        }
    </style>
</head>
<body>

  <p>
    <strong>Experienced Technologies</strong><br>
    This page highlights the programming languages, tools, and platforms I have experience with, along with the key libraries and frameworks I use for each. Click any library or framework to view its official documentation. As I rant about certain Technologies, They should appear here as well.
  </p>
    <table border="1" style="width:100%; border-collapse:collapse;">
      <thead>
        <tr>
          <th>Experienced Language/Tool</th>
          <th>Experienced libaraies / Frameworks</th>
          <th>Related Post</th>
        </tr>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <img class="icon" src="/assets/images/elixir.svg" alt="Elixir">
            Elixir
          </td>
          <td>
            <ul>
              <li><a href="https://hexdocs.pm/phoenix/" target="_blank">Phoenix</a></li>
              <li><a href="https://hexdocs.pm/ecto/" target="_blank">Ecto</a></li>
              <li><a href="https://nerves-project.org/docs/" target="_blank">Nerves</a></li>
            </ul>
          </td>
          <td></td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <img class="icon" src="/assets/images/ruby.svg" alt="Ruby">
            Ruby
          </td>
          <td>
            <ul>
              <li><a href="https://guides.rubyonrails.org/" target="_blank">Rails</a></li>
              <li><a href="http://sinatrarb.com/documentation.html" target="_blank">Sinatra</a></li>
              <li><a href="https://rspec.info/documentation/" target="_blank">RSpec</a></li>
            </ul>
          </td>
          <td></td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <img class="icon" src="/assets/images/javascript.svg" alt="Javascript">
            Javascript
          </td>
          <td>
            <ul>
              <li><a href="https://react.dev/learn" target="_blank">React</a></li>
              <li><a href="https://vuejs.org/guide/introduction.html" target="_blank">Vue</a></li>
              <li><a href="https://angular.io/docs" target="_blank">Angular</a></li>
              <li><a href="https://nodejs.org/en/docs" target="_blank">Node.js</a></li>
              <li><a href="https://expressjs.com/en/starter/installing.html" target="_blank">Express</a></li>
            </ul>
          </td>
          <td></td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <img class="icon" src="/assets/images/python.svg" alt="Python">
            Python
          </td>
          <td>
            <ul>
              <li><a href="https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/stable/" target="_blank">Django</a></li>
              <li><a href="https://flask.palletsprojects.com/en/latest/" target="_blank">Flask</a></li>
              <li><a href="https://pandas.pydata.org/docs/" target="_blank">Pandas</a></li>
              <li><a href="https://numpy.org/doc/" target="_blank">NumPy</a></li>
              <li><a href="https://fastapi.tiangolo.com/" target="_blank">FastAPI</a></li>
            </ul>
          </td>
          <td></td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <img class="icon" src="/assets/images/docker.svg" alt="Docker">
            Docker
          </td>
          <td>
            <ul>
              <li><a href="https://docs.docker.com/compose/" target="_blank">Docker Compose</a></li>
              <li><a href="https://docs.docker.com/engine/swarm/" target="_blank">Docker Swarm</a></li>
            </ul>
          </td>
          <td></td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <img class="icon" src="/assets/images/terraform.svg" alt="Terraform">
            Terraform
          </td>
          <td>
            <ul>
              <li><a href="https://registry.terraform.io/providers/hashicorp/aws/latest/docs" target="_blank">Terraform AWS Provider</a></li>
              <li><a href="https://developer.hashicorp.com/terraform/language/modules" target="_blank">Terraform Modules</a></li>
            </ul>
          </td>
          <td></td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <img class="icon" src="/assets/images/datadog.svg" alt="Datadog">
            Datadog
          </td>
          <td>
            <ul>
              <li><a href="https://docs.datadoghq.com/tracing/" target="_blank">APM</a></li>
              <li><a href="https://docs.datadoghq.com/logs/" target="_blank">Log Management</a></li>
              <li><a href="https://docs.datadoghq.com/integrations/" target="_blank">Integrations</a></li>
            </ul>
          </td>
          <td></td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <img class="icon" src="/assets/images/grafana.svg" alt="Grafana">
            Grafana
          </td>
          <td>
            <ul>
              <li><a href="https://grafana.com/docs/loki/latest/" target="_blank">Grafana Loki</a></li>
              <li><a href="https://grafana.com/docs/tempo/latest/" target="_blank">Grafana Tempo</a></li>
              <li><a href="https://grafana.com/docs/grafana/latest/plugins/" target="_blank">Plugins</a></li>
            </ul>
          </td>
          <td></td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <img class="icon" src="/assets/images/sentry.svg" alt="Sentry">
            Sentry
          </td>
          <td>
            <ul>
              <li><a href="https://docs.sentry.io/platforms/" target="_blank">Sentry SDKs</a></li>
              <li><a href="https://docs.sentry.io/product/integrations/" target="_blank">Integrations</a></li>
            </ul>
          </td>
          <td></td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <img class="icon" src="/assets/images/jira.svg" alt="Jira">
            Jira
          </td>
          <td>
            <ul>
              <li><a href="https://support.atlassian.com/jira-software-cloud/docs/" target="_blank">Jira Software</a></li>
              <li><a href="https://support.atlassian.com/jira-service-management-cloud/docs/" target="_blank">Jira Service Management</a></li>
              <li><a href="https://support.atlassian.com/jira-cloud-administration/docs/manage-apps-and-plugins/" target="_blank">Plugins</a></li>
            </ul>
          </td>
          <td></td>
        </tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>
</body>
</html>]]></content><author><name>Thomas M</name></author><category term="tech-stack" /><category term="work-experience" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[List of Technologies that I have experience in.]]></summary></entry></feed>